Guide to the Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E) Archived Websites MSS.616
Fales Library and Special Collections
Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E) Archived Websites
September 2015-September 2022
Fales Library and Special Collections
Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.)
MSS.616
37 websites in 37 archived websites.
This collection contains websites related to Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.), mostly documenting their web presence from 2015-2017. W.A.G.E. was established in 2008, to work for fair and regulated compensation for visual and performing artists in the non-profit arts institutions. The majority of their work operates around their W.A.G.E certification program and WAGENCY. The website includes historical information about the organzation; members of the certification program and how to become a member; and events, writings, and videos highlighting their activist work pressuring arts organizations to pay their freelance artists equitably.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
Arranged by date added to Archive-It.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
http://www.wageforwork.com/ was selected by Fales curators, likely Lisa Darms, and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. Additional websites in the collection were likely added to capture embedded and linked materials from the http://www.wageforwork.com/ domain.
Appraisal
Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored. Individual links were added to the web archives to capture all content associated with W.A.G.E. Websites were rescoped to attempt to capture the YouTube and Vimeo videos embedded in the websites.
Historical Note
Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.) was established in 2008 out of a series of discussions with artists and curators on their experiences with non-payment from art institutions. Out of these meetings, they wrote the wo/manifesto on economic inqualities in the arts sector. In 2010, they launched the W.A.G.E. Survey Report "to gather information about the economic experiences of visual and performing artists exhibiting in non-profit exhibition spaces and museums in New York City between 2005 and 2010." This led to the W.A.G.E. Certification program to recognize arts institutions that commit to paying artists a minimum standard payment. W.A.G.E. received non-profit status in 2011 and partnered with Artists Space to hold programming and investigate their artist compensation practice. In 2016, W.A.G.E. began its collaboration with Decolonize This Place, "an action-oriented space working around Indigenous struggle, Black liberation, Free Palestine, global wage workers and de-gentrification." In 2018, WAGENCY was launched, which certifies artists when they successfully negotiate fees and/or withhold art when organizations do not pay standard renumeration. In 2019, they released a report on the first 5 years of W.A.G.E. certification, W◼A◼G◼E◼ D◼A◼T◼A◼. As of 2022, 108 institutions are certified.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains websites related to Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.), mostly documenting their web presence from 2015-2017. The website contains information on their wo/manifesto; mission; history of the organization and history of artist organizing; board members; fundraising efforts specifically their Wages 4 W.A.G.E. campaign; writings on artist compensation; news; and events. A major focus on the website includes the 2010 W.A.G.E survey on artist payment from non-profit arts institutions and guidance on W.A.G.E. certification program and how to get certified. Many of their events and videos focused on publicizing the results of the survey and getting artists and institutions involved in the certification program. Other events include exhibitions and performance art exhibited by W.A.G.E. members, as well as conferences, meetings, and symposia focusing on activism in the arts sector. In 2016, they began publicizing their work on the WAGENCY program.
Art -- Economic aspects; Artists and community -- United States; Performance art.; Artists Space (Gallery)
- Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.), September 2015-November 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Scope and Contents
  Working Artists and the Greater Economy (W.A.G.E.) was established in 2008 out of a series of discussions with artists and curators on their experiences with non-payment from art institutions. The majority of their work operates around their W.A.G.E certification program and WAGENCY. The website includes historical information about the organzation; members of the certification program and how to become a member; and events, writings, and videos highlighting their activist work pressuring arts organizations to pay their freelance artists equitably.
- pOWER (100): A Screenplay YouTube Video, September 2015-September 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  2013 PREMIERE: W.A.G.E.'s brand-new infomercial-dramedy, pOWER (100): A Screenplay! W.A.G.E. take an off-the-cuff admission made by dOCUMENTA (13) curator Caroline Christov-Bakargiev at a recent panel discussion and create a fictionalized melodrama, a world where the very powerful curator finds herself treated like an artist! It's de(OCU)MENTED! Yeah...we're just crackin the FUCK(D) UP over here. Pass it on!
- Dear Arts Administrator YouTube Video, September 2015-September 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  WAGE, Working Artists and The Greater Economy, have made this commercial for the activist cause of securing standards of payment from art institutions in the United States.
- WAGE RAGE YouTube Video, September 2015-September 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  WAGE, Working Artists and the Greater Economy, made this commercial to advocate for systematic change to the abuse of artists' labor in the United States.
- WAGE WoManifesto YouTube Video, September 2015-September 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  WAGE, Working Artists and the Greater Economy, made this video to spread their manifesto around the world in advocacy of the rights of artists and art workers.
- Democracy in America: W.A.G.E. Vimeo Video, September 2022 (Box Electronic Records)
  Creative Time presents Democracy in America: W.A.G.E. (Working Artists and the Greater Economy) at the Park Avenue Armory. 2008. Video by Benjamin Brown.
- April 26: Martha Wilson: Activist History Teach-in, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Teach-in at the Shelley & Donald Rubin Foundation on April 26, 2017 featuring a performance of Matha Wilson's Martha Does Donald, and presentations by artists Ann Agee, Rehan Ansari, Tomie Arai and Betty Yu (Chinatown Art Brigade), Todd Ayoung (REPOhistory), Avram Finkelstein (ACT UP and Gran Fury), Alicia Grullón (Percent for Green), Amin Husain and Nitasha Dhillon (MTL), Rasu Jilani, Taja Lindley (Harriet's Apothecary), Katherine Perko, Gregory Sholette (Gulf Labor Artists Coalition), Lise Soskolne (W.A.G.E.), and Barbara Zucker (A.I.R. Gallery).
- Critical Issues in Contemporary Art Practice: Lise Soskolne, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Talk by Lisa Soskolne at the Henry Art Gallery on March 9, 2017 on the work of W.A.G.E. since 2008.
- Wages of Whiteness in the Art Economy, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Artists Space on December 10, 2016 on white supremacy in the art system and the racialized split between artists and art workers. The event was part of Decolonize This Place, a three-month project by art collective MTL+.
- W.A.G.E. Presentation, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Neu Kirche Contemporary Art on September 7 on the W.A.G.E certification program.
- Art + Money: Right to Work: Artists and Wage, with W.A.G.E, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Recess Art on August 18, 2016 on the W.A.G.E. certification program.
- Protected Blog, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Private page not captured by crawler.
- Artists at Work: A Conversation on Art and Labor, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Lecture at Boston University on March 23 on issues facing working artists.
- Chat Room, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Chat Room was a quarterly forum at the Northwest Film Forum on art in the age of the Internet.
- Charge 2016, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Charge 2016 was a three day event to platform artist led alternative models of sustainability; advocate for equitable compensation for artists; and consider artists' work in the larger economy. It took place at Art League Houston on January 8-10, 2016.
- Alliance of Artists Communities 2015 Conference, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Full schedule of 2015 Alliance of Artists Communities conference in Providence Rhode Island.
- On Value, May 2017-December 2018 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Artists Space on October 3, 2015 on the value relations of art production. It was part of We (Not I), a four-day program of discursive meetings, presentations, and events that brings together a wide range of artists, writers, curators and thinkers identifying with feminist practices to exchange and produce content addressing questions around the role of "we" in contemporary art practice,
- The Artist's Resale Right, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Artists Space on July 22, 2015 to discuss the American Royalties Too Act (ART Act).
- Art Handling Symposium, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Symposium at ALLGOLD on March 28, 2015 focusing on conversations between art laborers and art producers.
- art-agenda Dossier: Launch of two new Dossier projects, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Two project announcements of art-agenda Dossier: Dossier #3: W.A.G.E's online tool for determining compensation of commissioned digital artworks, and Dossier #4: Daniel Steegmann Mangrané's QR Constellation.
- Public Assets: small-scale arts organisations and the production of value, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  One day conference organized by Common Practice UK "to discuss the ways in which small-scale arts organisations produce artistic value beyond measurability and quantification, provide spaces for public experience extra to the market, and in so doing contribute importantly to cultural wealth." It took place on February 15, 2015.
- II. W.A.G.E.: How Creative Labor Should Be Compensated, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at CUE on December 11, 2014, where W.A.G.E. presented their research and advocacy regarding artists and earnings, minimum payment standards for creative labor, and certification for institutions that fairly compensate labor.
- charge, May 2017-December 2018 (Box Electronic Records)
  charge was a two day practicum to platform and convene artist led alternative models; open up conversations around equitable compensation of artists; and consider artists' work in the larger economy. It took place at Art League Houston on November 8-9, 2014.
- Projects at Common Practice New York, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Projects launched by Common Practice New York, including the publication Near Contact, by David Joselit and Amy Lien & Enzo Camacho; Out of Alternatives, a symposium on the role of small-scale arts organizations in New York City; Seminar and conference with the Center for Curatorial Studies at Bard College; and research papers by Rebecca Gordon-Nesbitt and Sarah Thelwall.
- Composing Differences, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at MoMA PS1 on April 27, 2014. Composing Differences "brings together artists, curators, researchers and others from Europe and the United States, who are establishing new platforms to experiment with art and knowledge production, which defend the circulation of knowledge and the immaterial value of art as a tool of social change."
- Simon Leung: ACTIONS!, May 2017-December 2018 (Box Electronic Records)
  Performance in September 2013 at the Kitchen reflecting on "actions" directed at the Museum of Modern Art from the 1960s to the 2010s.
- W.A.G.E. Survey Release, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at Artists Space on April 20, 2012 presenting the 2010 WAGE Artists Survey.
- W.A.G.E.: Feeling the Shape of the Arts Economy, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event in partnership with Artists Space on January 9, 2012. Event included a brief introduction to W.A.G.E. Certification; a presentation by artist, economist, and sociologist Hans Abbing, author of Why are Artists Poor: The Exceptional Economy of the Arts; and discussion.
- The Artist Theater Program: A Group Show of Film and Video Work by Visual Artists, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Group screening curated by Erika Vogt inviting visual artists who make use of film and video to present their work within the context of a theatrical exhibition venue. At the Roy and Edna Disney/CalArts Theater (REDCAT) on February 28, 2011.
- An Evening with W.A.G.E. (Working Artists and the Greater Economy), May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at the New Museum discussing the "Free" exhibition on December 9, 2010.
- "Free", May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  "Free" was an exhibition at the New Museum from October 20, 2010-January 23, 2011. "Free" explores how the internet has fundamentally changed our landscape of information and our notion of public space.
- W.A.G.E. Survey Report Summary, September 2015-May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  The W.A.G.E. Survey aimed to gather information about the economic experiences of visual and performing artists exhibiting in non-profit exhibition spaces and museums in New York City between 2005 and 2010.
- W.A.G.E. Teach-In, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Event at CCS Bard on April 14, 2009, held by W.A.G.E. members A.L. Steiner, K8 Hardy, and A.K. Burns.
- Navigating the Art of Change, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Article by Janet Brown published in the GIA Reader, Vol 20, No 1 (Spring 2009).
- NOBODY PUTS BABY IN A CORNER, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  NOBODY PUTS BABY IN A CORNER was a series of feminist gatherings in NYC through 2009-2010 initiated by Malin Arnell and Johanna Gustavsson, two Swedish artists attending the Whitney Independent Study Program.
- Human Resources, May 2017 (Box Electronic Records)
  Homepage for Human Resources, an arts organization in Los Angeles focusing on "contemporary and conceptual art, with an emphasis on performative and underexposed modes of expression."